Father Abbey's Will Collection, ca. 1739-1961: an inventory
Father Abbey's Will Collection, ca. 1739-1961
Harvard University Archives
HUG 1103.5
.19 cubic feet (1 flat box and 1 folder)
Father Abbey's Will, later attributed to Reverend Jonathan Seccombe (Harvard AB 1728), was a humorous poem first published anonymously in Boston in January 1732. The verses appeared after the death of the Harvard College Sweeper and Bed-maker Matthew Abdy in the early 1730s, and listed an inventory of Abdy's estate. A second poem purported to be a letter to Abdy's widow followed a month later. The poems were popular in both the colonies and England, and were reprinted as broadsides into the 19th century. This collection contains broadside, manuscript, and sheet music manifestations of the poem.
This document last updated 2011 January 13.
Acquisition information
The collection was assembled from various sources. Much of the collection is of uncertain provenance. Some items were purchased with Minot, Sheldon, and Welsh Funds or were received in the 19th and 20th century from donors. Photostats of originals not held by Harvard were received in the 20th century from the American Antiquarian Society, the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, the Boston Public Library, the John Carter Brown Library, and Yale University. Specific acquisition information is noted at the item level.
Researcher Access
The Father Abbey's Will Collection is open for research.
Related Materials
In the Harvard University Archives
Papers of John Leverett 1652-1724.
Poems copied by James Diman, ca. 1730-1733 (HUM 65).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Manuscript copies of Father Abbey's Will, undated
Series II: Broadside copies of Father Abbey's Will, ca. 1739-ca. 1800
Series III: Photostat broadside copies of Father Abbey's Will, ca. 1780-1797
Series IV: Sheet music of Father Abbey's Will dedicated to the Graduates of Harvard University, 1850
Series V: Materials about Father Abbey's Will, 1795-1961
Historical Note
Father Abbey's Will, later attributed to Reverend Jonathan Seccombe (Harvard AB 1728), was a humorous poem first published anonymously in Boston in January 1732. The verses appeared after the death of the Harvard College Sweeper and Bed-maker Matthew Abdy in the early 1730s, and listed an inventory of Abdy's estate. A second poem purported to be a letter to Abdy's widow followed a month later. The poems were popular in both the colonies and England, and were reprinted as broadsides into the 19th century.
Father Abbey's Will first appeared in the January 3, 1732 issue of a Boston literary newspaper, the Weekly Rehearsal, under the note: “On Saturday Night last, The LION King of Beasts, died at the Tan-yard in Water Street, Boston, where his Body may be viewed." The poem included the preface: "Cambridge, Decemb. 1731. Some time since died here Mr. Matth. A---y, in a very advanc’d Age, he had for a great Number of Years served the College here, in Quality of Bed maker and Sweeper…” The verses began, “To my dear Wife, / My Joy and Life.” The work listed each item of the Sweeper’s estate before ending “My days are done, / And so I think to leave it.” Five weeks later, a second poem to the widow “Mistress A---y” appeared in the February 7, 1732 issue with the preface: “New Haven, January 24. To the Author of the Rehearsal. SIR, Our Sweeper having lately buryed his Spouse, and accidentally hearing the Death and Will of his deceas’d Cambridge Brother, has conceiv’d a violent passion for the Relict.”
The unattributed Cambridge verse was printed two months later in the May 1732 issue of the London periodical Gentleman’s Magazine, and was followed by the New Haven verse in the June 1732 issue. The poems soon took on the title Father Abbey's Will and were published in magazines and as broadsides without attribution until November 1794, when the poems were reprinted in Massachusetts Magazine. The poem began with a preface, likely written by William Biglow (Harvard AB 1794), “I do not remember to have seen Father Abbey’s Will published in any late periodical work.---It was composed by Mr. [John] Seccombe, formerly minister of Harvard…” A letter to the editor, published in April 1795 by "F." rejected the claim, and said instead that the author was Joseph Seccombe (Harvard AB 1731). The magazine confirmed Rev. John Seccombe (1708-1792), a 1728 Harvard graduate, as the author in an August 1795 editorial titled “Certificate respecting the Rev. John Seccombe.” The editorial relied on information provided by Seccombe’s “only surviving classmate,” and private secretary to Governor John Belcher (Harvard AB 1699) in 1732, Thaddeus Mason (Harvard AB 1728). The article explained that Governor Belcher had forwarded Seccombe’s poems to London with a February 23, 1732 letter to his son Jonathan Belcher (Harvard AB 1728). In the letter, Belcher wrote, “I send the two Rehearsals for the sake of the Sweeper’s Will c, wrote (they say) by your classmate Seccombe, perhaps may bear reading in a London Coffee House.” In 1897, Nathaniel Paine attributed the New Haven verses to Colonel John Hubbard, a Connecticut physician, but in 1961 George T. Goodspeed concluded: “I have found no contemporary suggestion that Seccomb was not the author; on the contrary, his contemporaries Mason and Belcher believed that he was.”
Father Abbey’s Will and the New Haven reply were printed in broadside form into the 19th century. The poems underwent various word changes, and in 1850 the Cambridge verse was published as music by Oliver Ditson. At an undisclosed point, a four-line epitaph beginning “Thus Father Abbey left his spouse…” was added to the poem.
Biographical Note of Matthew Abdy
Matthew Abdy (ca. 1650-ca. 1730) was born in Boston around 1650. Abdy's appointment as the College Sweeper and Bed-maker at Harvard was recorded in the February 19, 1717/18 diary entry of President John Leverett. Abdy worked for the College until his death. The exact date of Abdy's death is unknown, but likely occurred in late 1730 or early 1731. Abdy married at least three times. His widow, Ruth Abdy, died on December 10, 1762 in Boston at the age of 93.
Biographical Note of John Seccombe
John Seccombe (1708-1792), a minister in Harvard, Mass. and later Nova Scotia, was born on April 25 in Medford, Mass. He received an AB from Harvard in 1728 and an AM in 1731. He was ordained as the minister of the town of Harvard, Mass. on October 10, 1733, but was dismissed on September 7, 1757. Seccombe and his family moved to Nova Scotia in 1759, and he served as a minister there until his death on October 29, 1792.
References
Ford, Worthington Chauncey. Broadsides, Ballads c. printed in Massachusetts, 1639-1800. The Massachusetts Historical Society, 1922.
Goodspeed, George T. "Father Abbey's Will" in Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society. Volume LXXIII, January-December 1961, pages 19-37.
Shipton, Clifford K. Biographical Sketches of those who attended Harvard College in the classes of 1726-1730. Boston: Massachusetts Historical Society, 1951.
Sibley, John Langdon. Father Abbey's Will; to which is added a letter of courtship to his virtuous and amiable widow. With historical and biographical notes. Cambridge: privately printed, 1854.
Scope and Content
This collection contains broadside, manuscript, and sheet music manifestations of Father Abbey's Will, and supplementary historical information. Following the poem's 1732 publication in the Weekly Rehearsal, it was printed in various formats through the mid 19th century.
The records are arranged in five series. Series I contains one handwritten copy of the poem likely made in the early 19th century, one undated photostat copy of a manuscript version of the poem, and a photostat copy of a poem titled "On the Death of Old Abdy Sweeper at Harvard College in Cambridge." Series II contains original broadsides of the poem and Series III contains photostat copies of broadsides not held by the Harvard University Archives. Series IV holds sheet music of Father Abbey's Will printed in 1850. Series V contains supplemental historical information about the poem.
George T. Goodspeed's 1961 article "Father Abbey's Will" in the Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society provides the basis for the organization of both the original and photostat copies of the broadsides in the collection. The broadsides are often undated and are difficult to differentiate; Goodspeed's article complements the collection by providing a comprehensive list of holdings at various institutions. There are two additional broadsides in the collection that are not included in Goodspeed's list. Of Goodspeed's list of broadside printings, the collection holds originals of numbers 1 [fragment], 5, 6, 9, 11, 14, and 15 (in Series II), and photostat copies of numbers 2, 3, 4, 7, 8, 12, 13, and 18. The collection does not have any copies of broadsides 10, 16, or 17. The broadside descriptions in this finding aid include the item numbers assigned by Goodspeed, as well as those used by W. C. Ford in Broadsides, Ballads c. Printed in Massachusetts, 1639-1800.
The titles of the broadsides vary and have been listed in the finding aid as they appear on each piece. While the earliest known broadside was titled "Father Ab--y's Will," the broadsides printed after 1780 refer to "Father Abbey." The verses originally published in January 1732 are referred to in the finding aid as the "Cambridge verse," and the verses published in February as a letter to Abdy's widow are referred to as the "New Haven verse."
Jonathan Seccombe's name is also spelled as Jonathan Seccomb, notably by Clifford K. Shipton in Biographical Sketches of those who attended Harvard College.
Series Descriptions and Item List
- I. Manuscript copies of Father Abbey's Will, undated, .03 cubic feet (3 folders)
  This series consists of a handwritten copy of Father Abbey's Will, a photostat copies of an undated manuscript version, and photostat copy of a poem titled "On the Death of Old Abdy Sweeper at Harvard College in Cambridge."
  A manuscript copy of Father Abbey's Will is included in a notebook of three poems copied by James Diman (Harvard AB 1730) held in the Harvard University Archives (HUM 65).
  - Father Abbey's Will, undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 1
    Handwritten copy of Father Abbey's Will, on one leaf of unlined paper. The Cambridge verse is written on the front of the document, and the New Haven verse is written on the verso. The document is attached to a second leaf of blank paper bearing the handwritten title "Copy of Old Ballad" on the verso.
  - Photostat copy of Cambridge in New England December ..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 2
    Received June 1960, the gift of Robert S. Clarke, Wood, Nash Co., London.
    Long and narrow six-page photostat copy of a manuscript copy of Father Abbey's Will.
  - Photostat copy of On the Death of Old Abdy Sweeper at Harvard College in Cambridge, undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 3
    Photostat copy of a three-page poem based on Father Abbey's Will, beginning "Ah mournfull found in Abdy ye small is dead / and with him all our ease and joy is fled." There is no provided information about the author, date, or owner of the original volume.
- II. Broadside copies of Father Abbey's Will, ca. 1739-ca. 1800, .09 cubic feet (9 folders)
  This series contains original copies of the broadside versions of Father Abbey's Will. identified as numbers 1, 5, 6, 9, and 11 by Goodspeed, and two additional broadsides not noted by Goodspeed or Ford. The descriptions in this finding aid include the item numbers assigned by Goodspeed, as well as those used by W. C. Ford in Broadsides, Ballads c. Printed in Massachusetts, 1639-1800.
  - Fragment of Father Ab--y's Will, [ca. 1739], HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 4
    Received in the Harvard College Library in 1932 from Hamilton V. Bail of New York.
    Goodspeed 1.
    Top half of a broadside with some text missing. The date is based on a "1739" watermark of the copy of the broadside owned by George T. Goodspeed.
  - Father Abbey's Will Cambridge, Dec. 1731. Some time since..., [ca. 1780], HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 5
    Received from the Saturday Club.
    Goodspeed 5, Ford 615.
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses divided by an ornamental rule. A wood cut of a building appears in the top-left corner. Handwritten note in the margin: "Father Abby's will to be preserved."
  - Father Abbey's Will, Cambridge, Dec. 1731. Some time since..., [ca. 1780], HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 6
    Goodspeed 6.
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge verses with the epitaph, printed in four columns divided by ornamental rules. Some text is missing and the broadside is backed with an 1845 advertisement.
  - Father Abbey's Will, To which is now added, a letter of courtship to his virtuous..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 7
    Received on August 31, 1877, the gift of Horace Brown (Harvard AB 1872) of Salem, Mass.
    Goodspeed 9, Ford 609.
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns. A wood cut of a man at a table appears on the top left; the same cut used in Goodspeed 8. At the bottom: "Sold at the Bible and Heart in Cornhill, Boston."
  - Father Abdy's Will. "Cambridge, December 1730. Some time since..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 8
    Purchased by the Harvard College Library on May 14, 1907 using Minot Funds.
    Goodspeed 11, Ford 614.
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge verses printed in two columns with an ornamental divide, without the New Haven verses or epitaph, but with a forty-four line "Epitaph on M. Abdy" beginning "Within this ground, there may be / found, / Old Matthew Abdy..." Includes two wood cuts: the top-left wood cut of a standing man, and the top-right wood cut of the same building as in Goodspeed 5.
  - Father Abbey's Will. To which is now added, a letter of Courtship to his virtuous..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 9
    Handwritten note on verso: "Given to me by [words crossed out] the 23 day of February 1827. J. S. B. Thacher," likely referring to Joseph Stevens B. Thacher (Harvard AB 1832).
    Goodspeed 14.
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns.
  - Father Abbey's Will. To which is now added, a Letter of Courtship to his virtuous..., [ca. 1800], HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 10
    Purchased by the Harvard College Library in September 1941 with the Sheldon fund.
    Goodspeed 15.
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns with wavy ornamental divides.
  - Father Abbey's Will. Cambridge, Dec. 1731. Some time since..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 11
    Not included on Goodspeed's list.
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses, printed in two columns. Includes woodcut of a man outside on top left.
  - Father Abbey's Will. To which is added, a letter of Courtship, to his virtuous..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 12
    Broadside copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns with ornamental divides by Nathaniel Coverly, Jun'r, Corner Theatre-Alley. Top-center woodcut of a man with a pipe. The broadside is backed by cardboard.
- III. Photostat broadside copies of Father Abbey's Will, ca. 1780-1797, .08 cubic feet (8 folders)
  This series contains photostat copies of original broadside editions of Father Abbey's Will held in other institutions, identified as numbers 2, 3, 4, 7, 8, 12, 13, and 18 by Goodspeed. The descriptions in this finding aid include the item numbers assigned by Goodspeed, as well as those used by W. C. Ford in Broadsides, Ballads c. Printed in Massachusetts, 1639-1800.
  - Photostat copy of Father Ab--y's Will. undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 1
    Received September 3, 1941 in the Harvard University Library with the Welsh fund.
    Goodspeed 2, Ford 610.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns.
  - Photostat copy of Cambridge, December 1731. Some time since..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 2
    Received in the Harvard College Library on August 2, 1937, the gift of Paul Hollister of Cambridge.
    Goodspeed 3, Ford 611.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns. Copied from the original in the John Carter Brown Library.
  - Photostat copy of Old Timothy Jobson. TO my dear Wife, my Joy and Life, [ca. 1780], HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 3
    Goodspeed 4, Ford 618.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge verses, considerably altered, without the New Haven verses or the epitaph. The original has notes in the margins regarding provenance. Copied from the original in the American Antiquarian Society.
  - Photostat copy of Father Abbey's Will. To which is now added, A Letter of Courtship to his virtuous..., [ca. 1780], HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 4
    Goodspeed 7, Ford 612.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns. Copied from the original in the American Antiquarian Society.
  - Photostat copy of Father Abbey's Will. To which is added, A Letter of Courtship to his virtuous..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 5
    Received September 9, 1941 in the Harvard University Library with the Sheldon fund.
    Goodspeed 8, Ford 608.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge and New Haven verses with the epitaph, printed in three columns. Top-left wood cut of man at a table; the same cut used in Goodspeed 9. Copied from the original in the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
  - Photostat copy of Father Abbey's Will: Cambridge, December 1730. "Some time since..., 1797, HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 6
    Copy made by the Yale University Library on March 6, 1945.
    Goodspeed 12.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge verse and the epitaph, printed in two columns with an ornamental divide, and published by Russell's Office. Includes large top-center wood cuts of a man (top left) and a dwarf in a chair (top right). Copied from the original at Yale.
  - Photostat copy of Father Abbey's Will. Cambridge, December 1730. "Some time since..., [ca. 1797], HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 7
    Received in the Harvard University Library on September 3, 1941 with the Welsh fund.
    Goodspeed 13, Ford 613.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge verse and the epitaph, printed in two columns with an ornamental divide, and published by Russell's Office. Includes large top-center wood cuts of a man (top left) and a child in a chair (top right); the same cuts used in Goodspeed 12. Copied from the original at the Boston Public Library.
  - Photostat copy of Father Abbey's Will. To my dear wife..., undated, HUG 1103.5 Box 2, Folder 8
    Goodspeed 18, Ford 617.
    Photostat copy of the Cambridge verse, printed in two columns with an ornamental divide. Includes three large top-center wood cuts of two outdoor scenes and an urn. There is no information available on the location of the original.
- IV. Sheet music of Father Abbey's Will dedicated to the Graduates of Harvard University, 1850, .01 cubic feet (1 folder); HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 13
  Received November 6, 1866, the gift of Harvard Librarian John Langdon Sibley (Harvard AB 1825).
  Sheet music for Father Abbey's Will published in Boston by Oliver Ditson.
- V. Materials about Father Abbey's Will, 1795-1961, .03 cubic feet (3 folder)
  This series consists of the 1795 article "Certificate respecting the Rev. John Seccombe," and photocopies of John Langdon Sibley and George T. Goodspeed's articles about Father Abbey's Will.
  - "Certificate respecting the Rev. John Seccombe," 1795 August, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 14
    One leaf (pages 301-302) of the August, 1795 issue of Massachusetts Magazine with an editorial regarding the authorship of Father Abbey's Will. The article identifies John Seccombe as the author based on information provided by "Thaddeus Mason, Esq. of Cambridge, the only surviving classmate, and very intimate friend of the Rev. John Seccombe."
  - Photocopy of Father Abbey's Will; to which is added a letter of courtship to his virtuous and amiable widow with historical and biographical notes, 1854, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 15
    Goodspeed 33.
    Photocopy of the pamphlet printed by Harvard Librarian John Langdon Sibley in 1854 from the original article in the Cambridge Chronicle, November 1854. Originals are available in the Harvard University Archives (HUG 1103.81).
  - Photocopy of "Father Abbey's Will" by George T. Goodspeed, 1961, HUG 1103.5 Box 1, Folder 16
    Photocopy of the article "Father Abbey's Will" by George T. Goodspeed published in the Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society, January-December 1961, Volume LXXIII, pages 18-37.